OK.
Let's get started.
So welcome back, everyone.
So today we're going to talk about parallelism.
And remember in the last week, we
introduced how to make a single GPU go fast by writing kernels.
And we really looked inside this GPU.
And this week, we're going to talk
about how to leverage multiple GPUs to make
your code go even faster.
So the picture you should have in your head
is something like this.
So for the last week, we focused on one of these boxes,
where you have your GPU.
Remember, you have your High Bandwidth Memory, HBM, L2 cache,
L1 cache, registers, and a bunch of streaming multiprocessors.
So now the picture gets extended,
because instead of having one GPU, you might have four,
you might have 1,000 GPUs.
And those are going to be connected.
And I'll talk later about how those GPUs are
going to get connected.
And then you're going to have to figure out
how to leverage all of this compute to train models.
So in both cases, meaning both in the single GPU case
and in the multi-GPU case, as we'll talk about today,
the situation is kind of similar if you zoom out,
which is that the compute, the arithmetic logic units,
the tensor core, and so on, is far away from your data.
And far away for a single GPU means all the way
over here in HBM.
And now if you have multi GPUs, the thing that you need here
might be all the way on a different GPU,
and you're going to have to shuffle that over somehow.
But the same principles are going
to be the same, because the game is
to orchestrate the computation to try to avoid data transfer
bottlenecks.
It's very easy to use a ton of GPUs,
but it's hard to use them effectively.
So taking a little bit of liberty,
we can think about the generalized hierarchy
where at the local level next to the SMs
a single node single GPU where you have an L1 cache
shared memory.
This was the fastest.
And then you had HBM, which we lamented was so slow.
But in this lecture, HBM is going to be considered fast.
Now we're going to think about the single node multi-GPU
setting where the GPUs are going to be connected
via NVLink and NVSwitch.
And then finally, the multi-node and multi-GPU,
where we have to resort to InfiniBand ethernet depending on what network you have.
So last week, we talked about various tricks
for reducing memory accesses, fusion and tiling.
Read into shared memory, do as much as you can,
and then write it back out.
And this week, we're going to talk
about how you can reduce the amount of communication
across GPUs by replicating and sharding appropriately.
So why do you do multi-GPUs?
The obvious answer is, well, you want to scale.
But to put a finer point on it, there's really two reasons.
One is that your parameters or activations or gradients
and optimizer state don't fit on the HBM memory of a single GPU.
So B21 has 192 gigabytes.
If you're training a 1 trillion parameter model,
that's not going to fit on a single GPU.
And the other reason is that even if your model could
fit on a single GPU, you might want
to leverage more GPUs by splitting everything up
to train faster.
So sometimes there will be some decisions
to be made because you could fit everything on GPUs,
but you have fewer cores.
But if you spread it out, then you're
going to have to pay the communication bandwidth.
So that's some calculation you're
going to have to do to figure out how to parallelize.
So just one note here is that so far this lecture is Python.
You execute it and you can just show everything.
Now, in this lecture, if you run this directly,
it uses multiprocessing.
But when I trace through it, I'm putting it in some
special single process mode.
So if you want to see the standard out
for this lecture run in the multiprocessing setup,
you can click here.
And I'll show this as we go through the lecture.
But just remember as we step through this lecture,
we're not actually doing multiprocessing,
because we're just stepping through single lines of code.
So this lecture is going to include two parts.
One is we're going to learn about the building
blocks of distributed communication and computation,
starting with the programming model.
Talk a little bit about the hardware.
Start to implement things in Torch,
which you're going to do on your assignment two.
And then the second part is we're going
to look at actual training.
We're going to look at three types of parallelism.
Data parallelism, tensor parallelism, pipeline parallelism.
Each is going to cut up our model in different ways.
We're going to do this for MLPs rather than
the full transformer.
But it's really the core computation
is going to be shown here.
So let's dive in.
So the first thing to talk about is these things
called collective operations.
So collective operations are these primitives from
distributed programming that go back to the '80s.
So the idea of parallel programming is very old.
It wasn't invented for LLM training.
And it's still the case that these primitives
are the ones that we use today.
And here, collective just means that you're
specifying a general communication
pattern or a template across multiple devices,
rather than managing point-to-point how
this GPU is going to communicate with another GPU.
And this is going to be much easier,
and the system can do a lot more work for you.
So this is a very tried and true interface
for doing parallel programming.
So the general setup is as follows.
The terminology here is a little bit--
I find it a little bit strange, but this is standard
in parallel programming.
The idea is that you have a bunch of ranks
where rank corresponds to a particular device, in our case
a GPU.
It could be a TPU.
But the point is that you have, let's say, four ranks here.
The world size corresponds to the number of devices,
so the world size here is four.
So there are a few operations we're going to go through.
Broadcast, scatter, gather, reduce,
all gather, reduce scatter, all reduce, and all to all.
And each of these operations is going
to specify how this set of ranks or devices
is going to transfer some amount of data
slash compute with it to some other set of devices.
So the first four, broadcast, scatter, gather, reduce,
are really just warm-ups, I would say.
They allow you to get a sense of how these collective operations
work, but they're not really going
to be the ones that are driving most of training.
All gather, reduce scatter, and all
reduce are the ones that are going
to show up again and again for distributed training of language
models.
And finally, all to all I'll just
mention here, which is important for MoEs,
but we're not going to actually spend too much time
on this in this lecture.
OK, so let's dive in with the simplest operation, which
is broadcast.
So in broadcasting, you have a rank 0.
It could be any rank, but let's just say, for the sake of picking
one, rank 0, has some tensor 0123.
And it broadcasts it to all the ranks.
So at the end of this operation, we have that each of the ranks
has the same tensor on it.
That should be pretty straightforward.
And this, again, doesn't really show up
in the core path of training.
Generally, broadcasts are used for initialization,
where, let's say, you initialize a load, initial checkpoint
and then you broadcast it to all the ranks.
So something that's done like once.
So the second operation is a scatter.
And a scatter basically says, I have a tensor at rank 0
who is split up into the world size.
And I'm going to basically scatter
my tensor onto the other ranks.
So rank 0 gets 0, the zeroth component.
Rank 1 gets this, rank 2 gets this, and rank 3 gets that.
So again, this is not directly used,
but scatter is an important stepping stone
to understand reduce-scatter.
So, as the name implies, scatter just takes a big tensor
at one place and spreads it out onto multiple places.
And you can see how this might be helpful,
because you want all the GPUs you're
scattering to do some local computation on the different parts.
So the inverse of scatter is gather.
So this should be very predictable.
The input is you have a bunch of pieces, each of which
reside on a particular rank.
And then when you do a gather, that's
with respect to a particular rank, rank 0,
it's going to just concatenate all the pieces together.
Again, gather isn't directly used,
but it's going to be a stepping stone to understand all-gather.
So next is reduce.
So those of you who do functional programming are
probably familiar with what reduce is.
It's exactly the same.
The idea is that you start in the same starting point
as a gather.
And where the tensor is split up across multiple-- well,
you have some piece of data on each of the different ranks.
And then you're going to apply your reduction
operation to all of these and get that in, put that on rank 0.
So in this case, if you do a reduction with sum,
then you add these all up, you get six.
So you can think about gather as a reduction
where the operation is concatenation, if you will.
And of course, reduce is important to understanding
all reduce.
So let me pause there.
Those were just the warm ups. Just in case people
have any questions about what a collective operation is,
broadcast, scatter, gather, reduce.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] NumPy, where is it?
So the question is, is this related
to broadcasting and NumPy?
I mean, I think it's conceptually the same idea,
where you have one thing that goes to many things.
Like in NumPy, if you have a scalar,
get broadcast to a tensor.
But the instantiation, this is for collective communication.
So it's a bit different.
So let's move on to something more interesting.
So all gather is what you do to-- basically,
you perform gather to all ranks, not just rank 0.
So remember what gather does.
It basically takes all the different pieces
and it just puts it on one rank, rank 0.
And now all gather just does it for every single rank.
That's what the all is for.
All means do it for all the output to all the ranks,
and gather is what you're doing to all the ranks.
So this is going to come up a bunch.
It's not important that you understand this statement
precisely, but later we'll see that each rank holds
part of the parameters.
And then what you need to do is all
gather the parameters to get the full parameters
for the full forward pass.
So in general, as we're doing training,
we're going to see a lot of this gather to do something
and then scatter and then gather and scatter again.
So reduce scatter is performing reduce on each dimension
and then scattering the results.
So let's say you have four devices and each of them
has some vector.
And so when we did a reduce before, we just had 0123,
and that got reduced to 6.
But now reduce scatter says that for each component
of this tensor, I'm going to do a reduction,
and then I'm going to put it on a different rank.
So the first dimension, I'm going to add these up, I get 6.
Now, for the second dimension, I'm going to add these up.
I get 10.
For third dimension, I'm going to process these.
For the fourth dimension, I'm going to process those.
So where this is going to show up, just to foreshadow things,
after the backward pass, when you sum what you're going to do
is each GPU will be dealing with different data.
And what you're doing is you need to sum all of the gradients
from the different shards.
And then you're going to redistribute this storage.
And then finally, all reduce.
If you understand all reduce, gather and all gather,
it's basically you do one and then you do the other.
So what this does is reduce scatter, the same input as we
had before.
And remember, in reduce scatter, we
had 6, 10, 14, and 18 sit on different ranks.
And the all gather part of all reduce just
puts them all on the same node.
So all reduce is in some sense the easiest to understand.
You have a bunch of tensors.
You reduce, in this case, sum.
And then you replicate them on all the nodes.
So we're going to see this one actually first
当我们进行数据并行并对梯度求和时
然后复制完整的参数。
所以这就是我们真正要开始的地方。
所以也许只需把注意力集中在 all reduce 上。
稍后，我们将看到如何实现更复杂的东西，比如 0
或 FSDP。
我们需要把 all reduce 拆分为 reduce scatter 和 all
gather，因为这样你才能介入
并且可以更好地管理这些事情。
但对于基本版本，all reduce 就够了。
最后，all to all。
这个在某种程度上是最通用的。
你基本上指定每个 rank 如何发送特定消息
到另一个 rank。
所以这里有一个简单的例子，其中你
拥有和之前相同的输入。
它表达的意思是，我
想把 0 发送到这个元素到 rank 0，
也就是保留在我自己这里。
我要把一个发送到 rank 1，两个
发送到 rank 2，三个发送到 rank 3。
然后如果我是 rank 1，我想把四个发送到 rank 0，五个
发送到 rank 1，六个发送到 rank 2，七个发送到 rank 3。
所以基本上，这里的位置
将表示哪个 rank
会成为最终目的地。
所以如果你看输出，会发生的是
第一个 rank 将接收所有
在列 0 中发送内容的人，因为所有这些 rank 都
把这些东西发送到 rank 0。
同样，对于 rank 1，所有的 rank
都发送这一列到 rank 1，依此类推。
所以这在训练 MOE 时会很有用。
这里的直觉是，每个 rank
既有数据的一个分片，也有一组专家子集。
基本上，MOE 的关键思想
是它是动态路由。
你必须查看你的数据，以确定
你需要把这些激活值路由到哪些专家。
所以它最终是一种 all to all 通信。
So if everything were balanced, meaning that every rank sent
the same number of bytes to every other rank,
then all-to-all, you can think about it
as essentially a transpose.
If you think about this as a matrix, all you're doing
is transposing that matrix.
But in general, all-to-all also handles unbalanced splits.
And I'm not showing this here, but you
can configure it to send any number of bytes
to any other rank.
But in general, you want the splits
to be as balanced as possible.
So remember the MoE lecture
where we had load balancing to make sure that things were as
balanced as possible.
So morally, the ideal goal is to have all-to-all
look kind of like this.
So just to summarize, maybe a few helpful tips to remember
the terminology, because I just went through quite
a few different operations.
So reduce is, well, it's reduced.
It performs some associative commutative operation.
Could be sum, could be max, could be min.
Scatter is the inverse of gather.
Scatter distributes, gather centralizes.
And all just means that the destination is all devices.
So that explains all-reduce and all-gather.
Let me pause there to take any questions
about collective communications.
Yeah?
For operations such as gathering where we basically
to rank 0, does that rank 0?
Is it a particular GPU every time or can that rank 0 change?
Yeah.
So the question is when you do a gather or a reduce,
the target where you write the output, right now I said rank 0.
You'll see later in the code, you basically
specify the GPU ID or the rank and it goes there.
So it doesn't have to be determined way in advance,
but it has to be determined basically
when you execute the call.
Cool.
Anything else?
Yeah.
These are just conceptual building blocks, right?
They're not actually [INAUDIBLE].
Are these the actual [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, so the question is, are these just conceptual building
blocks or are they code?
So I'm showing these right now as just conceptual building
blocks, but we'll very quickly see how
these are implemented in code.
So before getting into the code, I
want to talk a bit about the hardware,
in particular how GPUs are connected,
because we already what's inside a GPU.
So let's talk about networking in general.
So this is a very classic picture.
You can tell from this very old looking image
that this is how computers, I mean, generally work.
So you have this server and then you have a bunch of CPUs.
There's a PCIe bus, which you connect things like your--
or used to connect things like your mouse and keyboard.
And then you have a bunch of GPUs sitting off of them
and you have some RAM.
And then this computer is connected
to ethernet to another computer, and so on and so forth.
So this is a particular setup.
It's a particular topology.
And GPUs on the same node, you use PCIe to communicate and GPUs
on different nodes, you have to go all the way through ethernet.
So this is like if you bought your gaming GPU
and you had hooked it up with your friend and was like,
I'm going to train some big model.
That's what you would have to do.
But if you're really serious about training,
then things look more like this.
This is the picture I showed in the very beginning
where you have the GPU and there's
something called NVLink and NVSwitch and InfiniBand.
So the typical setup is this.
And these numbers, eight is typical,
but this 256 is kind of made up.
So typically, you have eight GPUs per node.
And these are connected via NVIDIA's NVLink to a switch.
And just for calibration, if you use NVLink 5,
then you're getting 1.8 terabytes
per second of total bandwidth.
And remember, HBM for B200 was 8 terabytes per second.
So it's about 4x slower.
So I mean, this is still pretty fast
if you think about going between devices, but obviously,
not as fast as high bandwidth memory,
which is much slower than shared memory or L1 cache.
So basically, NVLink connects to the switch,
which means that from a programming perspective,
you can think about GPUs as connected to any other GPU.
You go GPU to any other GPU, and the hardware
takes care of transmitting that to the switch,
and the switch routes it.
So typically, what you will also have is that at some point,
you can't have NVSwitch and NVLink.
Because as your number of GPUs grows,
then you're going to have to put these nodes into pods, which
are connected by InfiniBand.
And the way InfiniBand works is that now there's
a bit more the-- so now the GPU doesn't connect directly
to another GPU.
It has to go through PCIe and goes through this kind
of special InfiniBand cable.
And you see that the speeds are much, much lower.
And then finally, if you run out of InfiniBand you have these huge pods, then
you need to connect them via ethernet.
And in ethernet, you have to go through PCIe
and that actually goes through the CPU, which as we'll see,
is even slower.
So it's kind of analogous to the kind of memory situation.
The more nodes you have, then the slower it's going to be.
You can't have an NVSwitch handling 100,000 GPUs.
So one note is that I alluded to this bypassing
the CPU, which is going to be an important thing from a hardware
perspective.
So if you have traditional ethernet, what happens
is that the GPU has to talk to the CPU to get its data copied.
So it basically has to copy the data to this.
The CPU has a kernel socket buffer.
Here kernel means not the GPU kernel,
but the CPU, traditional notion of a kernel.
And then it has to build some network packets,
copy to the network interface, and then ship it over.
So this generally introduces a lot of latency.
And so there's this technology called Remote Direct Memory
Access, RDMA, which allows a GPU to directly write or read
from another GPU's memory without using the CPU at all.
So obviously, if you're in NVLink land and NVSwitch land,
then you have RDMA.
InfiniBand also supports RDMA.
So if you're connected via InfiniBand,
then you can directly have GPUs connect to each other
without involving the CPU.
But standard ethernet does not.
There's two notable advancements I will mention.
So NVIDIA has been really pushing
the limits on what you can do with larger and larger pods.
So they have four of basically the B200's and the B300's.
They have something called NVL72,
which means that they have these trays of eight GPUs
but have nine of them.
And so basically, at the end of the day,
you have 72 GPUs that are all kind of NV switched
into one NVLink domain.
And if you remember, the NVLink speeds are very fast.
So normally, if you're mortal, you
think, well OK, I have eight GPUs that
are interlinked really fast.
And then outside of that, then things get slowed down a lot.
But if you have a lot of money, you
can buy this really fancy hardware
and you can get really fast interconnects up to 72 GPUs.
And the other thing I'll mention is
我说过标准以太网不支持 RDMA，
但以太网这方面也有了进展。
所以有一种东西叫 RoCE，即 RDMA
over converged ethernet，其中以太网实际上
绕过了 CPU。
这算是他们对 InfiniBand 的回应。
InfiniBand 通常非常昂贵，
很多 NVIDIA 产品也是如此。
但你可以获得相当不错的性能
通过使用 RDMA over converged ethernet。
Meta 有一些论文表明他们正在探索这个方向。
所以 [INAUDIBLE] 可能是也可能不是
通过 converged ethernet 训练的。
这只是对硬件外观的简要概述。
你有 GPU。
它们通过 NVLink 连接到 NVSwitch，在一个域内，
可能是 8 个，也可能是 72 个。
然后从那里开始用 InfiniBand。
现在我们来谈谈如何对这个进行编程。
所以在最低层，有一种东西叫
NVIDIA Collective Communications Library，
NCCL 或叫 "nickel"，它把集体
操作，比如 all reduce、reduce broadcast，
转换成 GPU 之间发送的实际底层数据包。
NCCL 的作用是，当你使用 NCCL 时，
基本上就像在说，我想要 all reduce。
然后 NCCL 会去弄清楚硬件
的拓扑结构，找出
不同 GPU 之间的路径，然后
它实际上会启动 GPU kernel 来发送和接收
数据。
因为归根结底，记住，
在 GPU 上运行的一切都是 kernel。
所以也有通信 kernel，
它们实际上与其他 GPU 进行通信。
所以我们不会深入研究 NCCL，
只需要知道它存在。
然后我们实际上会转到 PyTorch。
所以也许在那之前，关于硬件有什么问题吗？
是的。
Can you describe—there's a rack and a tray.
Can I describe physically a rack and a tray, like what a rack is
and what a tray is?
So for the NVL72, so I'm not a hardware expert,
but a rack, I mean, is literally, I mean,
you've seen data centers, literally a rack.
And each tray is something that has—
so the G stands for a [? great. ?] So there's two CPUs.
And each CPU is connected to four GPUs.
So each tray has eight GPUs on it.
And they're stacked and everything
is connected to this NVSwitch.
Yeah.
Yeah, so the question is, what is the difference between
So RDMA, you can think about it as more of a desideratum.
RDMA means that one GPU can read and write
from another GPU's memory.
And there's multiple ways to do RDMA.
One is to use NVLink and NVSwitch
and another way is to use InfiniBand.
So InfiniBand and NVSwitch and NVLink
are more the hardware, what pieces, what cables and switches
are there.
And RDMA is more operation, what happens
when you're communicating.
Yeah.
For example, this [? advancement ?] RDMA
over converged ethernet is another way to do RDMA.
Yeah?
Is NCCL optimized for multi-node clusters?
Because obviously, it seems intuitive [INAUDIBLE].
But for RDMA based processes, would NCCL be optimal for that?
So the question is, is NCCL optimized
for multi-node clusters?
So I don't know the details of how they have or have not
optimized it.
All I can say is that NVIDIA has been basically optimizing
their entire stack for inference and training
of these large models, because their main customers are
the major providers of language models.
So I would be surprised if they haven't thought of optimizing
for those type of workloads.
Yeah?
So the question is, what happens if you have nine GPUs?
How do you distribute the workload across those?
I guess it kind of depends on how
the nine lands in your setup.
For example, a lot of times you'll have--
let's say you have eight GPUs per node.
So then the ninth one would be on a different node.
And if you don't have NVLink connecting them,
then that's going to be really bad, because that's
going to be one node which is not providing
that much compute and also very expensive to communicate with.
But if you, let's say, had everything
were connected by NVSwitch, then it
would be much more reasonable.
One more question and I'm going to move on.
So how is this different from TPUs?
So [INAUDIBLE] described TPUs a bit more.
So I mean, let's see.
What can I say quickly about this?
So TPUs are generally much simpler objects.
I'm not too familiar with the details of what
each of these components corresponds to,
but maybe we can talk about it offline.
So let's actually get down to some code
to take advantage of this hardware.
So PyTorch conveniently has a torch
distributed library that provides
a clean interface into these collective operations.
So you don't have to explicitly think about NCCL.
And in fact, this library also supports different backends
for different hardware.
So if you are on GPUs, then you would use the NCCL backend.
And if you were on CPUs, then there's
something called gloo which still allows you to--
Like I said, parallel processing has been around
for a long time before GPUs.
And you can do these collective operations on CPUs as well.
This library also supports higher level models
and algorithms such as SFTP, but we're not
going to use those in the course because we're building things
from scratch.
All right.
So let's walk through some basic examples
of collective operations.
So there's this function called spawn,
which takes another function I'm going to call,
and it says I'm going to run this replicated four times where
four is the world size.
So let's see what this does.
This is actually a wrapper I wrote just
to hack around the fact that I can't do multiprocessing
in this lecture.
So normally what you would do is you
call Torch's multiprocessing.spawn and you call the function.
But I'm going to do this branch which disables distributed.
So let's just go through that.
So now I'm in this function that it's
supposed to be running asynchronously for each process.
So remember, world size is the number of processes
and the rank is either 0 or 1 or 2 all the way up to world
size minus 1.
And so there are world size number
of these functions that are each running
on a process at the same time.
So I'm on rank 0 right now.
So what do I do?
There's a setup.
You basically configure the master address and port.
Notice that this is not actually how the GPUs are
going to communicate.
This is more for general metadata and coordination.
实际数据会经过 NCCL。
否则会非常非常慢。
如果你有 CUDA 可用，那么你
可以使用 NCCL 后端。
我在自己的笔记本上，所以我会使用 gloo 后端。
好，现在我来这里。
假设我有四个这样的进程在运行。
所以有一个 barrier 函数，它的用处是——
它是一个同步屏障。
所以基本上，如果我看到这个，那么它
会等待所有进程到达这个点。
所以基本上，你可以认为所有进程
都在异步运行。
所以我并不真正控制。
一个进程可能完全在另一个之前完成。
它们可能以任意方式交错完成。
所以如果我想确保
有些代码在其他代码之前执行，
我就会加入这些同步屏障。
所以现在加入更多屏障的缺点是
嗯，你最终可能会不必要地
等待。
那么让我们试一下 all reduce。
所以我要创建这个张量，0、1、2、3。
然后我有我的 rank。
为了让它更有意思，
每个 rank 会有一个不同的张量。
我要打印出我在 all reduce 之前有什么。
所以现在我要跳过这里，看看
会打印出什么。
所以 rank 0 在 all reduce 之前有 0、1、2、3。
Rank 1 有 1、2、3、4，依此类推。
这和我之前展示的例子一样。
注意，print 语句以任意顺序出现，
硬件想怎样就怎样，因为它是异步运行的。
但所有数据都在那里。
所以现在如果我做 all reduce，你传入——
这是一个 PyTorch 函数。
它传入这个张量。
你传入归约操作，也就是求和。
And I'm going to say don't do async.
And what this does is it calls, in this case, it would be gloo,
but it could be NCCL, in which case, it
would spin up the CUDA kernels.
It would do the communication.
It takes care of everything for you.
And then it basically writes in place to the data.
So after the all reduce, I have the all reduce operation,
remember, which is the sum of each of these columns
but replicated across all the ranks.
So that's all reduce.
And if you wanted to be fancier and do async,
then you could say async equals true.
But then it would screw up all these print statements.
So I'm trying to put more barriers than I would normally
would.
Yeah, question?
So the question is the rank the GPU.
For this class, the rank is the GPU.
So let's try another example here.
So I'm going to do a reduce scatter.
So here, I'm going to create an input, which
is 0 through the world size.
And I'm going to have the output.
I'm going to allocate the output.
And so what does this look like before I do the reduce scatter?
It looks like, let's see, this, where it's the same input
and the output happens to be zeros,
but it could be just anything.
And then I do the reduce scatter tensor.
Here instead of writing in place,
I have an output tensor and an input tensor.
I say I want to do the sum and then
afterwards, I get basically the input is not touched,
but the output I get the reduction
of each component written into the respective ranks.
So yeah, question?
So the question is, how does it work
to do the all reduce asynchronously?
So what this means is that this is like a monolithic operation.
You say go do the all reduce.
And it's spinning up CUDA kernels.
It's going to do the communication.
And remember, CUDA is already kind of async with respect
to the processes, and now we have
all the processes being async.
And the point is that this code just would return.
And then you could do other things.
So a typical thing, which I'm not
going to talk about this class, is overlapping computation
and communication.
So for example, you can do this operation,
and then you can go ahead and load some other data
for the next step, which is independent of this operation.
And then when you want to make sure that you actually are done,
then you can call a wait or a barrier.
So let's do the final one, which is all gather.
So by now, I think you get the idea.
Here I'm going to set as the input
the output of the reduce scatter.
I'm going to allocate an output.
So before the all gather, it looks like this.
I have my results from the reduce scatter here.
The output is just allocated.
It happens to have some values in it, but don't worry about it.
And then after I do the all gather into tensor,
and then I will have all the different inputs gathered
onto all the different ranks.
And you can see here that, indeed,
proof via example that all reduce
is equal to reduce scatter plus all gather.
And then just to wrap things up, just as I started by setup, then
I clean up, which it's good practice to clean up.
So that was your first example of a Torch distributed program.
So let's do some benchmarking.
This will be quick, since I want to actually move on to part two.
So how fast does communication happen?
So let's do an all reduce.
所以这里，我要对1亿个元素做all reduce。
哎呀。
抱歉，我把这里弄错了。
所以是all reduce。
所以我要创建这个张量
包含这么多元素。
记住，就像之前做基准测试时一样，
我们首先要预热。
这里我要调用Cuda synchronize，还要调用
barrier，只是为了确保，因为这里有
两种异步形式，Cuda kernel
和不同的进程。
我只是想确保一切
在开始计时之前都不再运行并且已经完成。
然后我要执行all reduce。
然后再用synchronize和barrier等待
并停止计时。
记住，这在每个rank上都会运行。
所以如果我看输出，这里rank 0、2、1、3，
我可能会得到不同的时间，
因为它们都是不同的进程。
每个进程都会报告某个测量值。
如果你想报告一个数字，
你可以取平均值，比如。
现在有一件有用的事情可以做，
这类似于我们之前计算MFU时做的事情，
就是测量有效带宽。
这里的想法是，好吧，这花了1.6毫秒。
这算好还是坏？
所以要计算有效带宽，我们
要做的是计算本质上
在这次计算中发送了多少字节，以及应该
发送多少字节。
然后如果你除以总时间，
就得到有效带宽。
所以我发送的数据大小，
是每个元素的大小乘以元素数量。
所以基本上就是这个数据张量的字节数。
实际发送了多少字节？
所以这需要一些拆解。
So for all reduce, if you think about,
let's just say for simplicity, you do a rank 0 plus rank 1
plus rank 2 plus rank 3.
You need to iterate this world size minus 1 steps,
because there's a world size minus 1 addition operations.
So that's this factor.
There's a 2, because you need to both send and reduce.
And then you multiply by the size of the payload.
So that's the total number of sent bytes.
And the total duration is the wall clock time that it took.
And then you multiply by the world size,
because it's the total amount that all the ranks have waited.
And the bandwidth is the bytes sent
divided by the total duration.
So in this case, you get something
like about 400 gigabytes per second.
So a few notes here.
One is that the effective bandwidth,
if you look at this expression, size times 2 times
world size minus 1 divided by world size times duration.
So as world size increases, this world size
minus 1 divided by world size essentially converges to 1.
So you're effectively left with 2 times the size
bytes over the duration.
So this is essentially the bandwidth.
Notice that this is independent of the world size,
which is good.
So if you grow the number of GPUs you have,
the bandwidth doesn't change.
It is also independent of the topology, which
is something that kind of NCCL figures out whether you're
going to pass the messages in a kind of a ring or a tree
topology.
So yeah.
So that is all reduce.
And for reduce scatter, this is very similar.
So I'm going to create the inputs and the outputs,
warm up, perform the operation, and time it.
So notice that the reduce scatter has these timings.
And you can also measure the effective bandwidth here,
the number of bytes that were in the input.
You have the number of bytes that were sent.
Here there is no 2x here.
And then the total duration, you divide by that,
you get the bandwidth.
So here, the bandwidth is--it should be very similar.
I guess sometimes there's some stochasticity,
but it's in the kind of 400s.
So a few notes here.
All reduce is, remember, as we stated, reduce
scatter plus an all gather.
And so all reduce, naturally, is moving twice the amount of data,
because reduce scatter has some cost, all gather has some cost,
and all reduce is doing twice as much work.
And it takes twice the amount of time.
But the two cancel out, so you get the same kind of bandwidth.
So that is the end of part one.
Maybe any questions before I move to part two?
Yeah.
Why did you do that synchronize for [INAUDIBLE]?
So why do we have to do the synchronize for the CUDA kernel?
So at the end of the day, we are still doing CUDA operations.
We have just multiple processes, each with a GPU,
doing some CUDA operations.
So if you're doing a CUDA operation, remember, by default,
it's async.
So when you reach the next line in Python,
that CUDA operation might not be done.
So we need to wait always to make sure it's
done by synchronizing.
[INAUDIBLE]
So do you have to do barrier first and then synchronize?
I'm not sure.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think one problem is if you barrier first
and then the CUDA might not be done running,
and you just immediately go to the barrier.
And then you are still each independently synchronizing
the different CUDA kernels, which means that you're not
really synchronized.
If all those operations just return,
the barrier doesn't really do anything.
OK, let me move on.
So now let's actually start thinking
about how you train models.
So we're just going to walk through a very bare bones
implementation of training MLPs, multilayer MLPs.
I guess that's redundant.
It's multilayer perceptrons already.
And remember that MLPs are the ones that
are the actual compute bottleneck in the transformer.
So this is actually pretty representative of what you'll see.
So data parallelism, tensor parallelism,
and pipeline parallelism.
And the picture I want you to have in your head
is this picture.
So this is a little bit of a schematic,
so don't think too deeply about this,
but it's more of a way to conceptualize how you're cutting
your data and parameters.
So data parallelism says, I'm going
to split the data into pieces.
And then each of the GPUs is going
to be responsible for part of the data,
and I'm going to just do normal—
I'm going to keep track of all the parameters
and do normal model training.
And then I need to synchronize.
So let me explain how this works.
So I'm going to generate some sample data.
So there's a batch size of 128.
Number of dimensions, 1,024.
So this is a batch size by num dim matrix, data matrix.
And let's jump into this data parallelism.
So the way that it's going to work
is that you have this data matrix.
And I'm going to break up the rows into world size pieces.
And in this case, four.
And each rank is going to get a piece.
So the number of dimensions, the batch size.
So I'm going to call the local batch size, basically the batch
size divided by the world size, which
is every row that GPU sees, it's going to have 32 data points.
And this is just indexing.
Start index, data start to end gets you the slice of that data.
And I'm going to just put it on that rank.
So at this point, each GPU has now
a distinct data tensor, which is the part
that they're responsible for.
Now, in practice, each rank should probably
load its own data rather than have this bottleneck,
but this is just for illustrative purposes.
So let's instantiate the MLP.
So here, I assume we have layers.
And num layers.
And for each of the layers, I'm going to have just a num
dim by num dim matrix.
So I'm just going to initialize a random set of parameters.
And then I'm going to feed that into optimizer.
So here's the training loop.
So in the forward pass, I take the data.
So remember, data is not all the data.
It's just if I'm rank 2, then I only get B2 part of the data.
I'm going to just go through the number of layers
and do a forward pass.
And then I'm going to do a backward pass.
And then normally, this would be it.
But now, remember, every rank has different data.
Therefore, the gradients are going to be different as well.
So this is the key step that makes data parallelism work.
We're going to synchronize the gradients
across all the workers.
This is the only difference between standard training
and DDP.
It's actually pretty nice and elegant.
So basically, for all the parameters,
I'm going to do an all reduce of param.grad.
And I'm going to average.
然后，all reduce 完成之后，现在在这个阶段，
每个 rank 都有完全相同的梯度。
然后我就直接更新参数。
所以我觉得这真的很优雅，
因为它基本上就是标准训练，你把它应用到
你的本地 batch 上，但只需插入这个
在反向传播之后。
让我们通过这个 all reduce 来平均所有梯度。
只需改一行代码，然后参数就被更新了。
所以在你训练时，每个 rank 基本上
都在进行参数更新，就好像它拥有全部数据一样，
但实际上它只处理了一部分数据。
所以这基本上就是 DDP，或者说第一种数据并行。
关于这个有什么问题吗？
是的。
[INAUDIBLE] 所以问题是，你只能
在 batch size 大于 1 的时候这样做吗？
是的。
所以你的 batch size 至少要等于 world size
才能真正合理。
而且通常，它应该要大得多。
是吗？
[INAUDIBLE] 是的。
所以问题是，batch size 应该是
world size 的倍数吗？
那也会很好。
是的。
我的意思是，如果不是，那你可以用零来填充
或者类似的方法。
所以有办法，但如果它是的话，对每个人来说都更简单。
[INAUDIBLE]？
对于基于 transformer 的 [INAUDIBLE] 会是什么样子？
是的，所以问题是，这会是什么样子
对于 transformer 来说？
实际上基本是一样的。
DDP 有一个很好的特点，就是非常模块化。
你做前向传播。
我的意思是，DDP 只是在这里平均参数。
它不关心你的前向传播是什么样子。
好的，让我继续。
So that's DDP.
So just to summarize, the losses are different across the ranks.
The gradients are also initially different.
But they are all reduced to be the same across the ranks.
And therefore, the parameters all
remain the same across ranks.
So next lecture, Tatsu is going
to talk about fancier data parallelism, FSDP and ZeRO.
And the idea there is, as I've alluded to,
here we use all reduce.
It's a very simple monolithic operation,
but it does require holding all the models, parameters
in memory.
But what if the model parameters don't fit in memory?
Then you're going to have to be more clever,
and that's the topic for the next class.
So let me talk about tensor parallelism.
So here, the idea is we're going to cut this way
and we're not going to cut the data.
We're going to cut essentially each layer.
And so each rank is going to get part of each layer.
And generally, this means that we're
going to have to transfer a lot more data.
We'll discuss this a bit later.
So what does tensor parallel look like?
So we're just going to assume we have this data.
Every rank has all the data just for simplicity.
And here, remember, the data is batch size times num dim.
And I'm going to define a local num dim to be-- for this rank, I only
am responsible for a subset of the dimensions.
So the picture here is that each model still has all the layers
here for all the layers, but the parameters now
are num dim times local num dim.
So if this were one of the parameter
matrices for one layer, I would be splitting down the columns.
So this is also known as column tensor parallel.
You can also do it by rows, but we're not going
to talk about that right now.
So now what does the forward pass look like?
So I'll go through all the layers
And I'm going to compute activations.
So I start with x, the data.
And I'm going to access the parameters at layer.
And notice that this is only a slice of the parameters.
So if I'm on rank 1, I only get this part of the matrix.
But I can still proceed.
I can apply this non-linearity, because this is element-wise anyway.
But now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to communicate activations.
So if I have a data matrix, rank 1
has activations for part of the activations
for this part of the matrix.
Rank 1 has part of the activations for this matrix
and so on and so forth.
And I need to basically put all the activations
on all the ranks.
But we know how to do that.
We introduced all gather as a collective primitive.
So this is all the activations.
So this is the batch size times local num dim, which is
the shape of the activations.
And then I'm doing an all gather.
Sorry, so this is the allocating memory for the activations.
So x is the actual part of the activation.
So this is batch size times local num dim.
And all gather says each rank has x and each rank
is going to allocate activations,
which is a list, one for each world size.
And then after the all gather, x is
going to be copied into each of the respective location
activations.
So then once I gather all the activations,
I concatenate them to form the full dimensional x, which
is batch size times num dim.
Any questions about column tensor parallel?
So this is done for every layer.
We now notice one difference between data parallel
is now we have to muck around with the model.
Data parallel is very elegant, because it's splitting by data.
The model is treated as a module.
But now we have to muck around with the model.
And this is strongly leveraging the fact
that if you want to do a matrix multiplication,
you can split it up into a set of smaller matrix
multiplications.
We can do those on different ranks,
and then we can gather the results.
When it comes to the backpropagation,
gradients are still [INAUDIBLE].
So now the question is, what happens in backprop?
Now, in the backprop, you have your activations
and you have to reduce scatter to all the different gradients.
So in some ways, all gather and reduce scatter
have this kind of duality, where in forward, you're
all gathering, in the backward, you're reduce scattering.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, is that done automatically by autograd?
So none of this--well, OK.
So if you just call .backward, it's not going to do it,
because there's no parallelism in that.
But PyTorch has all these things that
are done automatically for you.
[INAUDIBLE] To what extent do I need to change
my code and [INAUDIBLE]?
So what is done for you versus automatically?
Here we're managing things fairly explicitly,
which means I'm not doing the backward pass,
but you would have to manage and call the reduce scatter
yourself.
And that's by design, because this is 336,
building language models from scratch.
In practice, you probably wouldn't have to do that.
OK, so let's do pipeline parallelism quickly.
So the idea behind pipeline parallelism
is we're going to split the network this way.
So each rank is going to get a subset of the layers now.
Within each layer, it's going to get all the dimensions,
and it's also going to get all the--
Well, one of the ranks is going to get all the data.
Every rank is going to see all the data in some form.
So this is the way it's going to work.
So we have all the data, which is, again,
the batch size times num dim.
And I'm going to split up the layers.
So local num layers is going to be the number of layers
that a particular rank is going to handle.
And so now I'm going to have local params, which
is basically only-- there's local number of layers
number of them.
But within each layer, I'm going to do the num dim by num dim.
So one thing, maybe [INAUDIBLE] will talk more
about this on Wednesday, is this idea of micro-batches.
So maybe I'll just present this and explain
why I'm doing things this way.
So in addition to splitting up the layers,
I'm also going to split up the batch
into a bunch of micro-batches.
So if I'm rank 0, then I get the data,
and I'm going to chunk it up into a number of micro-batches.
And for each micro-batch, what I'm going to do
is receive it from the previous rank,
and then do the feed forward pass only on the layers that
are assigned to this rank.
And then I'm going to send to the next rank.
So here I'm actually using these receive and send,
which are pointwise operations.
So I didn't cover those before, but they're fairly explanatory.
This basically says I'm rank and I'm going
to send this tensor over to--
sorry, I'm going to receive this tensor from rank minus 1.
And this says I'm going to send tensor x to rank plus 1.
So basically, the reason why I'm talking about micro-batches is--
and [? Tatsu ?] will talk more about this on Wednesday--
is that in pipeline parallelism, so you have
one rank that gets the data.
It processes some of the layers, and then
it sends it to the next GPU, and it processes some of the layers.
And it then sends it to the next GPU.
So this is a very natural way of dividing a deep network.
But the problem is that you get these
what are called pipeline bubbles, where while you're not
processing, you're kind of waiting around for other tensors
to process.
And this ends up being quite inefficient.
So the idea behind micro-batches is that you break it up
into smaller batches, so you can process it quickly,
send it on to the next one.
So this can reduce the number of pipeline bubbles.
So the other thing I will mention
that is not handled in this very kind of naive version
is the idea of overlapping communication and computation,
which is actually very important to pipeline parallelism.
This basically gives you the right structure.
If you put an I before these, then it becomes kind of async.
You have to add more things to manage the code.
And the idea here is that you want to be--
while you're computing here, you can be
receiving data or sending data.
So computation and communication should overlap.
So that reduces the amount of time you actually spend waiting.
So a few things that are kind of missing here, which we'll
hopefully fill in next time.
So the communication versus computation overlap,
which is especially crucial in pipeline parallelism.
I didn't mention in data parallelism,
this also happens, because I just did a forward pass
and then at the end, I'm just doing all these all reduces.
But if you're clever, then on the backward pass,
as soon as the gradients are done,
you can start sending that.
And that's something that will be
explored in the assignment two.
And this, again, allows you to just overlap communication
and computation more.
We had some questions about what about general models.
Again, I think this MLP gives you
essentially most of what you need
for understanding the basics.
有些更大的模型需要更多的簿记工作，
所以更难看到核心算法。
还有一些我们没有讲到的其他类型的并行计算。
序列并行把一整个序列
切成若干块。
这样就可以并行化注意力
计算，专家并行则可以并行化
MoE 中的专家。
这就是我提到的 all-to-all 发挥作用的地方。
然后还有不同的组合
不同的并行化技术，这也会
出现在作业里。
需要注意的一点是，
你选择哪种并行技术
很大程度上取决于硬件。
例如，张量并行。
通信量很大，因为每一层
都需要发送所有这些激活值，而它们相当大。
所以通常张量并行发生在节点内，通过 NVLink
或者在高带宽的情况下。
而你不会跨 NVLink 域
做张量并行。
而流水线并行，你会看到有人在用。
通常它可以容忍慢得多的互连。
所以一些去中心化训练的工作
使用流水线并行，因为你的节点——
GPU 分布在世界各地。
但在那种情况下你不想做张量并行。
所以有时候你看这些组合，
会是节点内张量并行，
然后是流水线数据并行或 FSDP，
然后如果需要的话再用流水线并行。
还有其他影响，比如如果你做数据并行，
你可能可以把数据并行做得比较大。
但随后你会遇到一个
叫做临界批量大小的东西，这时
如果你把批量大小增加得太多，
它实际上并不会帮到你，这种情况下
你就是在浪费你的算力，
那你不如使用张量并行。
有很多这样的考虑因素，
随着课程的推进，我们会进一步讨论这些。
最后再说明一点。
刚才简单提到了TPU。
需要注意的是，我们有意使用PyTorch，
而且不只是使用PyTorch，而是真正以
非常基础的方式使用集体操作，
这样你就能从机制上看到发生了什么。
另一种方法，尤其是如果你在TPU领域，
就是你可以直接定义模型和起始
策略。
编译器实际上会处理很多
关于如何——
基本上，你需要什么样的通信操作。
你基本上是说，这块数据
需要在这里、这里和这里。
然后编译器会做一些神奇的事情来弄清楚。
所以这很有吸引力。
但显然，这会剥夺很多
从零开始构建东西的乐趣。
总结一下，有很多并行化的方式。
你可以按数据切分，按张量或专家切分，
按流水线或序列切分。
我们看了数据并行。
我们只做了DDP。
下次我们会讲FSDP和0。
张量并行，正如我提到的，
需要非常快的互连。
流水线并行则不那么需要。
但你需要非常努力地减少这些流水线
气泡。
然后也许在高层面上，我们
看到这个模式经常出现。
所以你可以选择重新计算或存储在内存中，
当我们讨论像
激活检查点或使用GPU时。
或者在这种情况下，你可以把这看作一种扩展，
即你可以存储在不同的GPU上。
从这个角度来看，你看数据并行。
在某种意义上，你在做冗余工作，
because every rank is actually updating its parameters
and keeping track of all the parameters.
But the reason you're doing that is
that you don't have to move the optimizer state across.
So one thing is that hardware is getting faster.
But in some sense, we'll always want bigger models.
So this idea of having a hierarchical structure
will always be there.
So that's it for today.
So next Wednesday, Tatsu will do more of a deep dive
on more parallelism techniques.